<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe discourse touching a broken heart In which the nature, causes, and signes of it are solidly treated of; as also, its acceptablenesse to God; together with many other motives pressing us to labour after the procurement of it, and the means leading thereunto: Being the summe and substance of certain sermons preached by Mr. Daniel Carwardine, late minister of Eling in the county of Middlesex. And since his death put forth by S.R. a friend of his. Whereunto is annexed, a confession of faith by Mr. Samuel Rowles, late fellow of Trinity-Colledge in Cambridge. And now minister of Thistleworth in the county of Middlesex.</title>
            <author>Carwardine, Daniel, b. 1600 or 1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230173</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896211</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153844</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81043)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153844)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2383:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe discourse touching a broken heart In which the nature, causes, and signes of it are solidly treated of; as also, its acceptablenesse to God; together with many other motives pressing us to labour after the procurement of it, and the means leading thereunto: Being the summe and substance of certain sermons preached by Mr. Daniel Carwardine, late minister of Eling in the county of Middlesex. And since his death put forth by S.R. a friend of his. Whereunto is annexed, a confession of faith by Mr. Samuel Rowles, late fellow of Trinity-Colledge in Cambridge. And now minister of Thistleworth in the county of Middlesex.</title>
                  <author>Carwardine, Daniel, b. 1600 or 1601.</author>
                  <author>Rowles, Samuel, fl. 1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 90, [8], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by E.G. for J. Rothwell, and are to be sold at his shop on the north-side of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A short confession of faith" has drop-head title and separate pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2383 lacks pages 25-48 of first part and pages 23, 24, 33-36 of second part.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Congregational Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A Briefe DISCOURSE TOUCHING A Broken Heart.</p>
                  <p>In which the nature, cauſes, and ſignes of it are ſolidly treated of; as alſo, its acceptableneſſe to God; To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with many other motives preſſing us to labour after the procurement of it, and the means leading thereunto:</p>
                  <p>Being the ſumme and ſubſtance of certain Sermons preached by Mr. <hi>Daniel Carwardine,</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>Eling</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſince his death put forth by <hi>S. R.</hi> a friend of his.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whereunto is annexed,</hi> A CONFESSION OF FAITH by Mr. <hi>Samuel Rowles,</hi> late Fellow of Trinity-Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now Miniſter of <hi>Thiſtleworth</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>J. Rothwell,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop on the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1652.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:2"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His little Treatiſe, if thou wilt pleaſe to peruſe it (as thou ſoon mayeſt) hath a very gracious and profitable deſigne upon thee, namely, to help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the great work of ſoftning and breaking thy hard heart, that ſo it may become a Sacrifice of a ſweet ſmelling ſavour to the great God, who delighteth in nothing wherewith the ſonnes and daughters of men can preſent him, more then in an humble and contrite ſpirit. I have ventured to call thy heart hard, whoever thou art that mayeſt caſt thine eyes upon theſe lines, taking it for a certain truth, that the hearts of all the
<pb facs="tcp:153844:3"/>
ſons and daughters, as well of God, as of <hi>Belial,</hi> are more or leſſe obdurate, if you conſider them abſolutely, though the hearts of good men may be called ſoft in compariſon with the hearts of wicked ones; or if compared with that greater degree of hardneſſe which was ſometimes upon themſelves, even ſince the time of their converſion. Such as doe take themſelves to have leaſt need of any helpes and furtherances in order to brokenneſs of heart, it is to be feared have of all men elſe the moſt. The Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which thought it ſelfe to have been rich (namely, in grace and holineſſe) and increaſed in riches, (that is, in a growing thriving condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, more holy every day then other) yea at length ſo rich as to ſtand in need of nothing, arrived at the very perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of grace, was (it ſhould ſeem) in the account of God wretched, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, poore, blind, naked, <hi>Revel. 3.17.</hi> uſually, by how much richer any man
<pb facs="tcp:153844:3"/>
is in ſpirituals, by ſo much poorer he is in ſpirit; and by how much poorer in ſpirit, by ſo much richer in ſpirituall ſubſtance. If I may meaſure thy wheat by my Buſhell, as <hi>Solomon</hi> gives me leave to doe, <hi>Prov. 27.19. As in the water face anſwereth to face, ſo the heart of a man to man.</hi> I ſay, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that maxime of <hi>Solomon,</hi> I can tell thee by the hardneſſe of my own heart, that there is ſome of that bitter root of obdurateneſs ſpringing up in thine. I would not doe thee ſo much wrong not knowing of thee (nor being ever able to know thy heart) as to ſay that there is ſo much of it in thy heart as in my own. But how little ſoever it is, you know what the Scripture ſaith touching leaven. <hi>A little leaven lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veneth the whole lump,</hi> ſo it is with the leaven of heart-hardneſſe. If thou look not to it in time, what our Saviour ſaith concerning Muſtardſeed, <hi>Matth. 13.31.</hi> thou wilt finde true in relation
<pb facs="tcp:153844:4"/>
to hardneſs of heart. <hi>Muſtardſeed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the leaſt of all ſeed, but when it is grown it is the greateſt of al herbs, and becommeth a tree, ſo that the birds of the ayre come and lodge in the branches thereof.</hi> Hardneſs of heart is at the firſt one of the leaſt ſinnes (not in reſpect of nature, but degree) for men doe ſet upon great ſinnes at the firſt with tenderiſh relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant conſciences, and ſoftiſh hearts, (hardneſs of heart being uſually intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced not meerely by the hainouſneſs of one ſinne once committed, but by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency and cuſtome in ſinning) but afterwards it grows up to be as a mighty tree (and well it may, ſeeing all ſinnes do contribute ſap and moyſture towards the growth of it) and then the birds of the ayre (I mean all ſorts of ſoring high flown wickedneſs) doe come and lodge in the branches of it; that is to ſay, are welcomed and entertained by means of it. When the heart of a man is
<pb facs="tcp:153844:4"/>
waxen hard, it becomes a very cage of unclean birds, an open houſe keeper to receive all ſorts of profane vagabonds. If thou art any waies prejudiced againſt this argument of heart-contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as too legall (which is the uſuall form of their Mittimus who doe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon ſoul-ſearching truth in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs) Tis legall doctrine, ſay they, away with it. I ſay, in caſe thou doſt apprehend this doctrine too legall (the common imputation caſt upon unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing truths) the enſuing Treatiſe will ſufficiently convince thee of thine error, if thou hadst rather part with it then keep it, when thou haſt light ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whereby to ſee that it is indeed an error. I need not tell thee how frequent a thing it is with Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the new Testament, to commend, encourage, and exhort unto humility, poverty of ſpirit, unfained repentance, godly ſorrow, all which expreſſions ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie no other then brokenneſs of heart,
<pb facs="tcp:153844:5"/>
and contrition of ſpirit, which ſome are ſo loath to heare of, and ſo upon a true account unwilling to come under the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of thoſe beatitudes &amp; benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons pronounced by ur Lord Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit, Bleſſed are they that mourne, &amp;c.</hi> Dareſt thou to lay any thing to the charge of that doctrine which Chriſt hath not onely juſtified by his preaching, but alſo crowned with his bleſſing, which alſo was much in uſe amongst the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who were exact followers of their Lord and maſter Chriſt. If God deſpiſe not a broken heart, but accepts it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in it, and dwels with it, take heed of entertaining undervaluing thoughts concerning brokenneſs of heart. Believe it, God will deſpiſe thee, and whatſoever proceedeth from thee, if thou deſpiſe it. What <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in reference unto preaching the Goſpel, <hi>1 Cor. 9 16. Neceſſity is laid upon me, and woe unto me if I preach not the Goſpel;</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:153844:5"/>
we may ſay the ſame in reference to bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe of heart: neceſſity is laid upon us (not a neceſſity of cuſtom or tradition but of commiſſion) and therefore woe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us if we preach it not. See our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for it, Heb. <hi>3.13 Exhort one another daily, leſt any of you be hardned thorough the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne.</hi> Even private Chriſtians are enjoyned to exhort one another for the prevention of hardnes of heart, how much more ought the Miniſters of the word to doe it yea the text ſaith, it muſt be done daily; and all little enough to keepe our hearts ſoft, which are as ſubject to be hard, as water that is taken of the fire is to waxe cold. (Reader) if thou art deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to have thy heart ſpiritually broken, (for ſo thou oughteſt to be, though many doe all they can to keepe their hearts from being broken,) thou mayeſt meete with many helpes and encouragements there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto (one or both) from ſeverall hands, namely, from the word and ſpirit of God;
<pb facs="tcp:153844:6"/>
from both law and goſpell, threatnings and promiſes, mercies and afflictions; from things within and things without thee, from the living voyce of Gods ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Miniſters, who cry as <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, <hi>Repent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand;</hi> as alſo from the publike, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of Gods ſervants who are dead and gone; and amongſt the reſt from this little worke which is the onely orphan expoſed to publike view of a late reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and godly Miniſter who now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth from his labours. The worke is of ſo very ſmall a bulke that thou mayeſt reade it over in a few houres, but of ſo great difficulty in reſpect of practiſe, that thou canſt make no great proficiency therein in many dayes, weekes, or yeares, unleſſe thou gird up the loines of thy minde and ſet about it with all earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Such was the modeſty of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor that he could never be prevailed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by any importunity to ſuffer any thing
<pb facs="tcp:153844:6"/>
of his during his life time to come neere the preſſe, nor yet to conſent to it after his death. But that ſome of his friends deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to erect a memoriall of him and to make him ſerviceable to the publicke as well ſince his death as in the time of his life have uſed him not unlike to Sauls uſage of the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> (though with a better Conſcience and intent, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him forth as it were from the grave into the Land of the living (where he was content to have laine in perpetuall ſilence and obſcurity, till the day of the revelation of all things. The ſeaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſubject was one of the maine inducements moving thoſe to get it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed whoſe deſire it was to bring it forth into the light. And it muſt needes he granted that this argument was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more ſeaſonable then now it is, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart and haughtineſſe of ſpirit being an epidemicall diſeaſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age, as he that runs may reade. And yet never leſs complaining of hard hearts
<pb facs="tcp:153844:7"/>
then now a dayes: but I wonder not at that it being the nature of this diſtemper to ſteale upon men ſo inſenſibly that they do not onely not perceive it of themſelves, but are alſo let looſe to an inapprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch diſcoveries as ſpirituall phyſitians doe make unto them of their being under the power thereof though they ſhew them ever ſo many ſymptomes to evince the truth of what they charge them with. That I lay no falſe imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the men and women of the preſent age, in ſaying that their hearts are generally hard above meaſure, is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to make appeare from ſeverall clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e demonſtrations; I ſhall give you but one which is this, we finde by ſad experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that the worke of converſion is very much at a ſtand, few there be that are taken in the net of the Goſpell in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of what had wont to be, yea we heare not of many who come ſo farre as to be pricked at the heart and put that neceſſary queſtion, what ſhall we doe to
<pb facs="tcp:153844:7"/>
be ſaved? whence ſhould this proceede but from the generall hardneſſe of mens hearts more then formerly. The word of God is as quick and powerfull, as ſharp and piercing now as ever it was, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it in its ſelfe, for theſe are inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble properties of the word of God, as we reade <hi>Heb. 4.12.</hi> but the hearts of men are not ſo pliable as heretofore, they are become law proofe and goſpell-proofe more then ever, in ſuch a ſenſe as we call that kinde of armour which no bullet oan enter, armour of proofe. But I have no pleaſure in upbraiding men with the hardneſs of their hearts, we had much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be imployed in provoking them to labour after the ſoftning and mollifying of them that they may ſend forth a fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant ſmell into the noſtrils of the great God (as ſpices being bruiſed are moſt fragrant.) If thou wilt ply this worke of labouring to breake thy heart Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, beſides all thoſe excellent helpes, whereof I told thee before, which doe moſt
<pb facs="tcp:153844:8"/>
willingly offer themſelves to thy aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: there are others thou mayeſt have for preſſing and compelling ſuch as thou little dreameſt of, namely the Divell the world and the fleſh, all and every of which by the power of God and grace may be made uſe of towards the breaking of thy hard heart. If thou take this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for a riddle, the meaning of it is this; the people of God reflecting upon, and laying to heart thoſe motions of ſin which are continually ſtirring in them, as alſo thoſe ſeverall temptations both from the divell and world, whereunto they are daily and hourely obnoxious are hereby greatly humbled and abaſed in their own eyes as <hi>Paul</hi> was by reaſon of the body of death which he carryed about with him, and the Meſſenger of Sathan which was ſent to buffet him. Surely this was the engliſh of that good mans paradox, who ſaid he had ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived hurt by his graces, and good by his ſins, the good which his ſins did him
<pb facs="tcp:153844:8"/>
ſurely was no other then this, that they did ſerve to humble him and make him poore in ſpirit. Though it be a very ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and excellent imployment to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the riches of Gods love revealed in the Goſpel, and to rejoyce therein: yet this is not a Chriſtians onely worke whileſt he ſojourneth in this vale of teares, as ſome would repreſent it who affect this kind of ſublimity in the ſtate of grace which is proper for and conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent onely with the condition of glorified Saints in Heaven. If we could imagine ſinne to be in Heaven there would be occaſion for ſorrow and brokenneſſe of heart even there alſo; becauſe there are certain actions in the ſtate of grace, ſinfull actions committed by us, which ſhall never be in the ſtate of glory. Thence it is, that there are paſſions and affections alſo proper for this ſtate, which ſhall be done away in that; as ſorrow brokenneſs of heart, &amp;c. Surely Christ was no whit angry with
<pb facs="tcp:153844:9"/>
                     <hi>Peter</hi> (but rather well pleaſed at it) for weeping bitterly, after that he had denyed his Lord and Maſter. When <hi>Peter</hi> did flow with teares, then did Chriſt caſt an eye of compaſſion towards him. The enſuing diſcourſe will furniſh thee wiih many motives unto brokenneſs of heart, I ſhall therefore ſpare the labour of mentioning any, ſave onely this one conſideration tending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, namely, that the heart of man is almoſt the onely thing amongst all created things that remains unbroken. I ſay, there are few pieces of the creation round about us, but have been or are exceedingly broken, were not the apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing Angels greatly broken when they were caſt down from Heaven like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and thruſt into the nethermoſt hell? Is not the image of God in man exceedingly broken and defaced in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of what it was in the ſtate of innocency? are not the ſeverall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſouls of men, their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,
<pb facs="tcp:153844:9"/>
wils, affections, conſciences, memory, wretchedly broken by that fall, ſo that they are nothing like to what they would have been, if man had ſtood in his primitive glory and excellency. We have now broken apprehenſions of things, leaking memories, like to broken veſſels, broken inclinations to good in our wils, like bowles that are not halfe biaſsed. If we looke upon the law of God, hath not that beene miſerably broken by us, and yet is from day to day? Our duties and performances are they not for the moſt part, yea altogether broken and imperfect things, like children borne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their full time, weakely heartleſſe things? Our very graces are they not broken and imperfect habits full of mixture and adulteration, our Faith mixed and as it were ſophiſticated with unbeliefe, our humility with pride our ſelf-deniall with ſelf-ſeeking. If we looke upon thoſe creatures which are below us, is not their primitive excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb facs="tcp:153844:10"/>
greatly abated and impaired by the fall of man, as the Apoſtle inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates when be ſaith. <hi>That the whole creation is made ſubject to vanity, by reaſon of him who hath ſubjected it:</hi> that is to ſay, ſinfull man. As for the Civill State, in how broken and unſettled a condition that is for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I neede not tell thee: for that is the breach whereof the generallity of men are but too too ſenſible. And as for the Church of God it ſelfe, is not that in a broken ſhattered condition, now if ever? are not profeſſors of Religion all to pieces almoſt in every place? I had almoſt compared the condition of the Church at preſent to a ſhip that is wracke, here ſwims one planke, there another, It may be ſcarce two whole planks to be found together. The Lord helps us, what ſad and numerous or rather innumerable breaches are in the midſt of us at this day. And yet alas, our hard hearts do ſtil remaine unbroken. Adde to all that
<pb facs="tcp:153844:10"/>
hath been ſpoken, that thou who readeſt this booke haſt, it may be, many breaches in thy holineſſe, many in thy peace, ſeverall breaches in thy name, eſtate, friends, and comforts of every kinde; and yet perhaps after all this a heart in a greate meaſure hard and unbroken. It it great pity that ſhould not be broken of all the reſt, were that broken as it ſhould be, it would conduce to the making of all the reſt whole againe. It is indeed a difficult worke to breake a hard heart; but thorough Chriſt enabling thee thou mayeſt doe that and all things elſe: be ſtrong therefore in the Lord and in the power of his might, and ſo goe forth to encounter this mighty Gyant, thy hard heart, I meane, Wreſtle with God in prayer for a ſoft heart, and reſolve not to let him goe till he have bleſſed thee therewith, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did in another caſe. Begge of him who triumphed over prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallities and powers, and made an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſhew of them upon his Croſse, which
<pb facs="tcp:153844:11"/>
was the time of his greateſt humiliation that being now exalted to the right hand of his Father he would enable thee to triumph over thy hard heart, which is his enemy no leſſe then thine, and to make thee more then conquerour on that behalfe. He that hath promiſed to break the Serpents head can with greateſt eaſe break thy heart. And who can tell but that he may pleaſe to doe it, at leaſt in part, with the little hammer of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing diſcourſe, if thou be willing to come under the ſtroke of it. If this little Treatiſe, with the bleſſing of God upon it, ſhall proſper in thy hands (or heart rather) as I deſire with all my ſoule it may) give God the glory; and ſeeing the author himſelfe is where thy prayers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach him, where and where only the people of God are indeed above all ſuch duties and ordinances (I mean heaven) ſubſtitute me in his roome as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of thy hearty remembrances at the throne of grace: which if thou ſhalt pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:153844:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to doe, I ſhall thinke my ſelfe well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed for my poore endeavours in the perfecting and publiſhing of it for thy uſe and benefit, as alſo obliged to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſerviceable to thee, as God ſhal here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after enable me, Farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine in the ſervice of the Goſpel, SAMUEL ROWLES.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Study in</hi> Thiſtleworth, <date>
                           <hi>March 26. 1652.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:12"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:12"/>
                  <head>A TREATISE OF Brokenneſſe of Heart.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal 51.17.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>The ſacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit; a broken and a contrite heart O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He title of this Pſalm ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us both the Author (or rather Penman) and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, being ſtiled a Pſalm of <hi>David,</hi> when <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet came unto him, after he had gone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> which ſtory you may reade at large in, 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 12.1. and ſo onwards. The Pſalm it ſelfe doth excellently ſuite the occaſion, being full of humble and ſorrowfull ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the greatneſſe of his offence, as you may ſee <hi>verſe</hi> 3:4. <hi>I acknowledge my tranſgreſſions and my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153844:13"/>
ſinne is ever before me. Againſt thee, thee onely have I ſinned and done this evill in thy ſight, &amp;c.</hi> ſo likewiſe in other verſes of the chapter. And as he condemnes himſelfe, ſo likewiſe doth he expreſſely own the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God in the judgement which was denounced againſt him, as it is written <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>That thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be juſtified when thou ſpeakest, and be cleare when thou judgeſt.</hi> You have alſo in ſeverall verſes of this Pſalm earneſt ſupplications made unto God (doubtleſſe with ſtrong ſighs and groanes) by this holy penitent Prophet; as in the firſt place, that God would take away the guilt of his ſinne, ſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>According to thy tender mercyes blot out my tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> 2. That God would take away the filth of his ſinne, ſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Waſh me thoroughly from mine iniquities, and cleanſe me from my ſinne.</hi> 3. That God would preſerve him from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153844:13"/>
into the ſame ſinne or ſinnes of like nature; for which purpoſe he prayes, <hi>v.</hi> 10. that God would create in him a cleane heart; probably in reference to his uncleane ſin And in the 14 <hi>verſ.</hi> that God would deliver him from bloud-guiltineſſe, proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with relacion to his having ſhed the innocent bloud of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah.</hi> In the fourth place he begs of God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore unto him the joy of his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to make him heare joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that the bones which he had broken might rejoyce. Furthermore he promiſeth unto God, that if he will doe for him according to the tenor of his requeſts, namely pardon his ſinne, he will thorough his grace inabling him, teach tranſgreſſors his wayes, and be inſtrumentall that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners may be converted to him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as alſo that his tongue ſhall ſing aloud of his righteouſneſſe and his mouth ſhall ſhew forth his praiſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153844:14"/>
                     <hi>verſ.</hi> 14, 15. If God did ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ſacrifice and burnt offrings, he ſaith he would not ſpare for them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>Thou deſireſt not ſacrifice, elſe would I give it.</hi> If thouſands of rams and whole rivers of oyle might have beene acceptable to God, he would have offered them with all his heart. But he knew there was ſomewhat elſe which God did more looke at then all the burnt offrings and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices that he could preſent him with; of which he makes mention in the words of the text, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>The ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of God are a broken ſpirit.</hi> It is put in plurall number, <hi>The ſacrifices of God,</hi> for emphaſis ſake, thereby intimating that a broken heart is more worth to God then many out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſacrifices; yea, then all of them put together, not, but that other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices were of ſome account with God in <hi>Davids</hi> time, eſpecially if they were joyned with this inward
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153844:14"/>
ſacrifice of a broken heart; but this alwayes had the preheminence in Gods eſteeme, even in thoſe dayes when he did appoint ſo much out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip to be uſed. Of the verſes which doe follow the text we ſhall need to ſay nothing; onely this we may obſerve from them by the way, namely, that <hi>David</hi> was not unmindfull of the Church its pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke good, when his heart was as full as it could hold of griefe and ſadneſſe by reaſon of the weight and burthen of his ſinnes, together with the abſence of the light of Gods countenance, which was ſo grievous to him, that he ſaith, it broke his very bones, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>That the bones which thou haſt broken may rejoyce.</hi> A high expreſſion indeede: you know that ſickneſſe and ſadneſſe may weare a man to nothing but skin and bone; may make a very Anatomy of him, and yet never a bone of him be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153844:15"/>
broken thereby<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet when <hi>David</hi> was in this low bone-broken condition he forgets not the Church of God, but prayes heartily for it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>Do good in thy good pleaſure unto Sion and build thou the walls of Jeruſalem:</hi> of this by the way. Returne we to the words of the text. <hi>The ſacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi> It were needleſſe to divide the words being one ſingle propoſition. The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which is held forth in them we ſhall commend unto you in theſe words.</p>
                  <p>Doct. <hi>A broken heart, a ſoule hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for ſinne is a ſacrifice well pleaſing to God;</hi> you have this truth averred once and againe in this Pſalm, yea in this one verſe. Firſt, In that a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart is called Gods ſacrifice; it is thereby intimated to be well pleaſing to him; God will not own thoſe things for his, he will not call them by his name which he hath no
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153844:15"/>
pleaſure in. <hi>Is this ſuch a faſt as I have choſen, to hold downe his head of a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh, and to ſpread ſackcloth and aſhes under him?</hi> wilt thou call this a faſt, &amp;c. Iſaiah 58.5. as if God ſhould have ſaid, wil you offer to call ſuch a faſt as this, my faſt? Gods faſt? It is no faſt of mine, It is your own, you have not at all faſted unto me in this. That which makes for our purpoſe is, that God will not have that called his, which is not pleaſing to him. So then foraſmuch as a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart is called Gods ſacrifice, this very expreſſion, if there were no other, doth ſpeake it that which pleaſeth him. But there is another expreſſion or two in the text which are obſervable for this purpoſe. The one is, that a broken heart is called The ſacrifice of God; which you know is a note of eminency; as when we ſay, Chriſt was the word of God, that is the word of words,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153844:16"/>
the eſſentiall word: or Chriſt is the Sonne of God, that is, the Sonne of God in a more ſpeciall way, namely by eternall generation. Secondly, In that a broken heart is ſaid to be the ſacrifices of God and not onely one of the ſacrifices of God; it ſpeaks as if this ſacrifice were inſtead of all others, did containe all other ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in it <hi>eminenter</hi> (as Philoſophers ſpeake) as if God could be ſatisfied with ſuch a ſacrifice as this, though he had no other but this, &amp;c. But the third and laſt expreſſion in the text is moſt emphaticall, <hi>A broken and a contrite heart O God thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi> Here are two expreſſions uſed to ſignifie brokenneſſe, namely broken and contrite, which may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thus much to us; that if the heart of a man be ever ſo much bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſhattered with ſenſe of, and ſorrow for ſinne, be a man ever ſo vile and worthleſſe in his own eyes,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153844:16"/>
though he account no more of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, then of a broken potſheard or earthen veſſell that is daſhed in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet God will not therefore deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe, nay indeed he will reſpect him the more for it. Though men are wont to trample when the hedge is low, and to ſlight thoſe that are in a broken condition, broken in their eſtate, and broken in their ſpirit by much ſadneſſe, yet God will not doe ſo. There is much in this phraſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that God will not deſpiſe, &amp;c. It is a plaiſter which doth excellently fit the wound of a broken heart. That which men in ſuch a condition are wont chiefly to fear is, that God, who is a great, a glorious, and holy God, will not vouchſafe to take notice of ſuch poore vile ſinful creatures as they are; or of any thing which can come from them. They think they are as vile, yea more in Gods eyes then they are in their own. As if God
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153844:17"/>
ſhould have ſaid in ſo many words by the mouth of his Prophet, I know what poore broken-hearted ſinners doe thinke, their ſecret thought is, that I will deſpiſe them, becauſe they are ſo deſpicable in their own eyes. No ſuch matter, ſaith God, by his Prophet here, appealing to God. <hi>A broken and contrite heart O God thou wilt not deſpiſe;</hi> that is, thou wilt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, thou wilt have reſpect unto it, thou wilt ſmell a ſavour of reſt from it, as from a well pleaſing ſacrifice, &amp;c. So much of the truth of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine evidenced from Scripture. In the further purſuance thereof we ſhall this doe; namely, ſhew you in the firſt place what this broken heart is which is ſaid to be a ſacrifice well pleaſing to God; &amp; wherein it doth conſiſt. Secondly, what it is that cauſeth brokenneſſe of heart. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, why it is that God will not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe a broken and contrite heart, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153844:17"/>
accepts of it as a ſacrifice ſo well pleaſing to him. Of theſe in their order. 1. <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart here ſpoken of, or wherein doth it conſiſt? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here to we ſhall give anſwer, Firſt, more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, Secondly, more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Firſt, In the generall take this account of it. Brokenneſſe of heart is a true griefe and ſorrow in the ſight of our ſinnes. Heart-breaking as well in Scripture phraſe as in our common language denotes deep ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; ſo it is taken <hi>Act.</hi> 21.13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>What doe you weeping and breaking my heart,</hi> ſaid <hi>Paul,</hi> to thoſe who diſſwaded him from going to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which you know is the ſame as if he had ſaid, why doe you thus grieve me, and fill me with ſorrow at my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by weeping over me. We may alſo gather, that by heart-breaking is meant ſorrow; foraſmuch as God is ſaid to dwell with him who is of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153844:18"/>
an humble and contrite ſpirit, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive him; which reviving preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth drooping and ſadneſſe. The ſoule that is not caſt downe with ſorrow needes no reviving. But eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kinde of ſorrow is not the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe of heart here ſpoken of, but onely that kinde of ſorrow which we ſpake of even now, namely, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſinne. There is a ſorrow cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>worldly ſorrow,</hi> or heart breaking, which is ſaid to worke death, God hath no pleaſure in ſeeing his people breake their hearts after ſuch a faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nay, he hath commanded that in reſpect of outwards men ſhould be ſo far from breaking their hearts with ſorrow, that they ſhould mourne as if they mourned not. But godly ſorrow which is ſaid to work repentance never more to be repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, that is the brokenneſſ of heart here commended, as may appeare from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. where a broken heart
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153844:18"/>
is twice in one verſe joyned with an humble heart, as being convertible termes. <hi>I dwell with him that is of an humble and contrite ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble and contrite.</hi> Now you know that great trouble of ſpirit occaſioned by outward croſſes is not true humility; for ſuch affliction of ſpirit may ſtand with great pride and great hardneſſe of heart; yea, it may ariſe from pride. By how much more proud the heart is, by ſo much more will it rage and take on when it meetes with oppoſition; like waves that ſwell and roare and daſh themſelves in pieces againſt thoſe rocks which ſtand in their way. If you looke alſo into the 66 chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> verſ. 2. there are two paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in that verſe which doe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that by brokenneſſe of heart muſt needs be meant ſorrow for ſin, and not any other kind of ſorrow. A broken heart is there called a poore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153844:19"/>
ſpirit, and a ſpirit which trembleth at the word of God. <hi>To him will I looke that is poore, and of a contrite ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp; that trembleth at my word.</hi> Now a man may be much broken with afflictions, and yet be farre from that poverty of ſpirit to which Chriſt pronounceth the bleſſing, <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in ſpirit.</hi> A mans heart may be as much lifted up within him when he is poore, naked in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſpects, as if he were rich and full and wanted nothing. It is onely a true ſight of ſinne which can work true poverty of ſpirit. So whereas a contrite heart is ſaid to tremble at the word of God, you know that is uſually a fruit of mens being ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their ſinnes, and not of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward troubles, to make them trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the word of God. Thus have we proved to you, that by broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart is meant a true and godly ſorrow for ſinne. Come we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153844:19"/>
now to ſhew you more particularly, wherein this brokenneſſe of heart doth conſiſt, which is as followeth. It doth conſiſt firſt in a thorow con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of the ugly nature of ſin. I call that a thorow conviction of the uglineſſe of ſinne, whereby men are not onely inclined to thinke of ſinne as an ugly deformed thing, but are altogether perſwaded that it is ſo, and doe no more queſtion it then they queſtion the uglineſſe of any thing which is abominable to the eye or againſt which they have, a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural antipathy. As thoſe that have a natural antipathy againſt any kind of creatures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or rather we may deſcribe a thorow conviction thus, namely, it is ſuch a conviction of the loathſomeneſſe of ſin as is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to perſwade with men to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the forſaking of it. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that we doe define brokenneſſe of heart to conſiſt in a thorough
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153844:20"/>
conviction not meerly of the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe of ſin or evil conſequences thereof, but in conviction of the ugly nature of ſinne as it is contrary to the holy nature and righteous law of God; ſee a text for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe namely <hi>Iob.</hi> 42.51.6 <hi>I have heard of thee with the hearing of the eare, but now mine eye ſeeth thee; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe I abhor my ſelfe and repent in duſt and aſhes.</hi> That which made <hi>Iob</hi> abhor himſelfe was the ſight of God; and how did that doe it? why thus; the more he beheld God, the more he did obſerve his own contrariety to God by reaſon of ſinne; whence ſprung that ſelfe abhorrence of his. And this is the firſt particular where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in brokenneſſe of heart conſiſts. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It conſiſts in true mourning for ſinne. They goe about to divide betwixt things that are inſeparable, who ſay their hearts are affected with a true hatred of ſinne, and yet are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153844:20"/>
not broken with reall ſorrow for ſinne. Hatred of ſinne and ſorrow for the commiſſion of it doe alwayes goe together. In the 12 of <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah verſ.</hi> 10. you have the repentance or broken heartedneſſe of the Jewes, which is there prophecyed of, thus deſcribed. <hi>They ſhall tooke upon me whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourne for him as one mourneth for his only Son, and ſhall be in bitterneſſe for him as one that is in bitterneſſe for his firſt borne.</hi> Thirdly, in ſhame of heart and ſoul that we have ſinned. Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in reſpect of ſinne doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly attend broken heartedneſſe, yea our being aſhamed of ſinne doth much helpe to breake our hearts for ſinne. See what is ſaid of broken-hearted <hi>Ephraim, Ier.</hi> 31 19. <hi>After I was inſtructed I ſmote upon my thigh, I was aſhamed; yea even confounded becauſe I did beare the reproach of my youth.</hi> Broken-hearted ſinners reflect
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153844:21"/>
upon the dayes of their vanity before converſion, as a great reproach to them. They bluſh to thinke what they were before God called them, I was a blaſphemer; a perſecutor, an injurious perſon, doubtleſſe with no ſmall ſhame he ſpeaks it; If one that were afterwards a great perſonage advanced to ſome great preferment had formerly been a ſcullion or kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin boy, how aſhamed would he be to be told of it; yea if he did but thinke of the meane offices which he had done in his time, it would much abaſh him, eſpecially if he were a man of a proud ſpirit. So broken hearted ſinners when they call to minde what baſe drudges they have beene to ſin and Satan, &amp; what ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did worke they have been imployed in by them formerly, it filleth them with ſhame and confuſion of face; not becauſe their ſpirits are proud (for this is not pride in them) but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153844:21"/>
becauſe they are raiſed up to a holy diſdaine and contempt of ſinne, as of that which is the greateſt badge of diſhonour that can cleave to them. Noble perſonages are not more aſhamed of having their bloud ſtained by treaſon, then broken hearted ſinners are of thoſe ſtaines of ſinne which have cleaved to them. Nor are they onely aſhamed of the dayes of their vanity, but alſo of the vanity of their preſent dayes, &amp;c. Fourthly, broken heartedneſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in ſelfe-denyall and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to forſake ſinne for the time to come. A broken heart is alwayes a ſelfe-denying heart, and it muſt needes be ſo, becauſe broken hearted perſons are very ſenſible of their own unworthineſſe, and conſequently apt to thinke every good thing too good for them, as he that ſaid, he was leſſe then the leaſt of all the mercyes of God. The reaſon why
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153844:22"/>
men are ſo hardly brought to deny themſelves, in any thing which may any wayes gratifie them, is this, namely, becauſe thorough the ſelfe-love that is in them, they doe thinke nothing too good for themſelves. Now when humility and broken heartedneſſe hath once taken men of from this conceipt, and made them to thinke the quite contrary, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that every thing is too good for them, they can ſafely deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this or that which they would otherwiſe ſeeke to enjoy. By how much more of ſelfe denyall is in any man by ſo much more is there in him of broken heartedneſſe; and by how much more of broken heartedneſſe, by ſo much more of ſelfe denyall. You know that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous inſtance of the Prodigall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to his father with a broken heart, <hi>Father,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Jam unworthy to be called thy ſonne, make me as one of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153844:22"/>
thy hired ſervants.</hi> A broken heart will deny it ſelfe in many things; as for example, not onely in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which it might have in repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſins formerly committed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which it doth firmly reſolve, in the ſtrength of Chriſt: but alſo in thoſe lawfull actions w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may any waies give occaſion unto relapſing into former ſins, or be any appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſetting their faces towards them. Yea ſuch a perſon wil be apt to deny himſelfe in the lawfull uſe of that which he hath formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, through exceſſe, as wine, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, recreation, &amp;c. 5. It conſiſts in (or rather is alwaies accompanied with) ſelf accuſing and condemning before God Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth wil ſpeake. Perſons that are full of ſelf judging wil fall to ſelf accuſing, and from thence to ſelf condemning. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel (who is called the accuſer of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153844:23"/>
the brethren) might ſpare himſelfe that labour, foraſmuch as broken hearted ſinners are as forward to accuſe themſelves, as he can be. How highly doth <hi>Paul</hi> charge himſelfe, whom he cals <hi>the greateſt of ſinners. David</hi> doth much accuſe himſelfe in this and ſeverall other Pſalms, and condemn himſelf alſo. For then is a man ſaid to condemn himſelf, when he acknowledgeth that God were moſt juſt if he ſhould condemn him, in reſpect of any argument which can be drawn from himſelfe to the contrary; what may be alledged to the contrary in reference to his ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Jeſus Chriſt, is another matter, &amp;c. Men that Phariſee like doe ſtand upon their terms, and goe about to juſtifie themſelves before God; I do not ſpeak of pleading their ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (for that is lawful in ſome caſes) but rather their innocency in a great degree, as if they were no great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153844:23"/>
but like the cloud which the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> ſaw, at the firſt of the bigneſſe of a mans hand; ſinners of a ſmall ſize, I ſay, they who ſo juſtifie themſelves may talke much of broken heartedneſſe, but they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew indeed and in truth what it meant. Men that take up a new faſhioned kinde of praying (new in reference to thoſe prayers which are recorded in the word, as alſo which have beene uſed amongſt Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple generally) leaving out the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſinne, and taking of ſhame to themſelves for it, it is to be feared have their hearts little broken in that duty. Sixthly, broken hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe conſiſts in ſelfe abhorrence, as was inſtanced before in <hi>Job.</hi> A man that hath a noyſome diſeaſe upon him; as an overſpreading leproſie, &amp;c, is not onely offenſive to others, but alſo loathſome to himſelfe. He is an abomination to himſelfe, ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153844:24"/>
that he could even leape out of his ſkin, if he knew how. So it is with broken hearted ſinners: they are even an abhorring to themſelves, by reaſon of the leproſie of ſinne which cleaves to them. Hence <hi>Paul</hi> cryed out, O wretched man, who ſhould deliver him from his body of death which he carryed about with him? Becauſe he could not tell how ſinne and his body could otherwiſe be parted, then by parting ſoule and body; he did long to be rid of his very body. As a man that is given to cleanlineſſe, if any vermine come neere him, begins to be ſicke of him ſelfe, or at leaſtwiſe of his cloathes, and longs till he be ſhifted. So <hi>Paul</hi> did long to put off his mortall body, becauſe the loathſome vermine of ſinne did breede in it doe what he could; and to put on immortality, in which condition, all filth would be done away. You know ſinne is
<gap reason="missing" extent="24 pages">
                        <desc>〈24 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:153844:24"/>
mitted. As it is amongſt friends in the world; though they truly love each other, yet becauſe there are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine differences betweene them for the preſent uncompremiſed, ſuch courteſies as may be offered on either hand, for the preſent will not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. It is the complaint of the Church unto God, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.44. <hi>Thou haſt covered thy ſelfe with a cloud that our prayers ſhould not paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough.</hi> It was a time in which God had led his people into captivity for the hardneſſe of their hearts, and it ſhould ſeeme that was not all, but he did alſo for the preſent ſtoppe his eares againſt their prayers, looking upon them as yet not ſufficiently humbled, and heart broken for their ſinnes. 4. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This ſhould put us upon examination whether we have broken hearts or not. And believe it, there hath beene much ſaid to put us upon diligent inquiry thereinto, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch
<pb facs="tcp:153844:25"/>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153844:26"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:153844:26"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:153844:27"/>
as we have proved it to be a ſacrifice well pleaſing unto God; Who would not think it worth his while to enquire, whether himſelfe and his ſervices be ſuch as God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts? <hi>Queſt.</hi> But how may we come to know whether our hearts be truly broken for ſinne or not? <hi>Anſ.</hi> For the diſcovery hereof, you may have recourſe unto the deſcription of broken heartedneſſe laid downe in the beginning of this diſcourſe: in which we told you that brokenneſſe of heart did conſiſt in theſe ſeverall particulars, namely, in a thorough conviction of the ugly nature of ſin. Now put the queſtion to your hearts; are you convinced of the evill of ſinne, after ſuch a manner as is there deſcribed? nextly, in being really aſhamed of ſinne? Now doe you finde this alſo, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſinne is matter of great ſhame and confuſion of face to you? that you looke upon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153844:27"/>
ſinne as that which is your great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach? Thirdly, what mourning and relenting of heart is there in you for the commiſſion of ſinne? is it matter of griefe and lamentation to you? Fourthly, hath the ſight and apprehenſion of your ſinnes brought you to the unfained deniall of your ſelves, looking upon your ſelves as leſſe then the leaſt of the mercies of God, by reaſon of them? Fifthly, are you come to that paſſe, as even to loath, abhor, and be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your ſelves by reaſon of ſinne? Sixthly, doe we judge, accuſe, and condemne our ſelves before God ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely for ſinne? adde hereto a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth ſigne of broken heartedneſſe, which hath not as yet beene men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and that is, doe we really pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thoſe that hang downe their heads, and are perplexed by reaſon of ſinne? men that have been in the ſame condition with others who are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153844:28"/>
in any kinde of miſery are moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to pitty and commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Upon this account it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>that we have not a high Prieſt who knoweth not how to be touched with our infirmities; in as much as he was made like unto us in all things, ſinne excepted.</hi> It is alſo thus written, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. <hi>For in that himſelfe hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red being tempted; he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</hi> Men that have beene exerciſed with any kind of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily infirmities, as gout, ſtone col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, are beſt able to pitty thoſe who have the like infirmities; So they who have themſelves known what belongs to a broken heart, will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it by their ſympathy with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who fall into the ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Not but that it is matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing to ſee the hearts of our friends broken with godly ſorrow, if we conſider the fruit and effect of it, but if we conſider it meerely as it
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153844:28"/>
is in its ſelfe, what is ſaid of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is true of brokenheartedneſſe: <hi>No affliction is joyous for the preſent, but grievous; but it worketh the peaceable fruits of righteouſneſſe for them who are exerciſed therewith.</hi> So broken hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe is not joyous for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and in that regard it calls for pitty and ſympathy, though it doe afterwards worke the peaceable fruits of righteouſneſſe. We pitty our friends when their Phyſicke doth make them heart ſicke, though we know it will doe them good in the concluſion. Thus much ſhall ſuffice of the uſe which is by way of examination, &amp;c. 5. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> this ſhould exhort us to labour to get broken and ſoft hearts. For motives whereunto conſider theſe following particulars which are reducible to two generall heads: 1. The dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, evill, and inconvenience of a hard unbroken heart. 2. The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153844:29"/>
of a ſoft, broken heart, under each of which we might ranke many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars &amp;c. The evills enſuing upon a hard heart are as follow: 1. God will not accept, but reject an hard heart, together with all that which proceedes from it, &amp;c. See <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Breake up your fallow grounds, ſow not amongſt thornes, circumciſe your ſelves to the Lord, and take away the foreskins of your hearts, leſt my fury breake forth like fire, and burne that none can quench it.</hi> How farre is the great God from accepting thoſe, the fallow ground of whoſe heart is not broken up, ſeeing he doth here threaten, that the fire of his wrath ſhall break forth upon them, and there ſhall be none to quench it. <hi>And thou by thy hard and impenitent heart,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>treaſureſt up to thy ſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath.</hi> That is, all any man ſhall get at the hands of God by a hard heart, namely, a treaſure of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153844:29"/>
wrath; you know that God doth chiefly eye with what hearts men do bring their ſervices before him: So that if men pray with ever ſo much appearance of zeale and fervency, if they faſt ever ſo often, if they give ever ſo much Almes to the poor, if they make ever ſo large profeſſions of religion, &amp;c. and their hearts under all this doe ſtill remaine hard and unbroken, it is as if they had done nothing at all. All their bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe will profit them very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle &amp;c. 2. A hard heart will ſhut out all that which would come to doe us good. If we have hard hearts, mercies will not winne us, judgments will not affright us. Looke how it is with men of harſh diſpoſitions and and inflexible natures, uſe faire meanes to them, and you ſtirre them not, uſe fowle meanes, and they are ſtill at the ſame paſſe of inſenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: you had as good threaten a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153844:30"/>
wooden poſt, or ſpeak to it friendly, and it would be to as much purpoſe as to threaten ſuch men or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate them friendlily. Juſt thus it is with a hard heart. It is like ſtony rocky ground, no ſeede of grace will thrive there, how ſhould faith thrive in a heart that is inſenſible of ſinne? will they goe to Chriſt for life, who apprehend not that they are loſt, and dead in themſelves. How ſhould repentance flouriſh there, where ſin is not felt? how ſhould they love God much, who doe not apprehend that they have many ſinnes, which had neede to be forgiven? A hard heart is ſo farre from being better for mercies, that it waxeth worſe and worſe under them. It turneth the grace of God into wantonneſſe, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe judgement is not ſpeedily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed upon the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, therefore is the heart of the children of men ſet to doe evill. And
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153844:30"/>
not onely ſo, but they doe take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion by the judgments of God alſo to waxe worſe and worſe. As they are ſmitten they revolt more and more, like the ſmiths anvill, the more it is beaten upon, the harder it growes. The more plagues God did ſend upon <hi>Pharoah,</hi> ſtill the more hard and inſenſible he did grow. A hard heart is like the clay that is made more hard by contrary cauſes: both by the warme ſunſhine, as alſo by the cold froſt. If God put not more then ordinary efficacie into the meanes, a hard heart will rather be worſe then better for them, &amp;c. 3. We can never hope upon good grounds to enter into Heaven with unbroken hearts. None ſhall dwell with God hereafter but thoſe with whom God dwels here. Now the text ſaith, that God doth dwell with him that is of an humble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart, thereby intimating that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153844:31"/>
God dwels not with them that are of proud unbroken hearts. <hi>Thou by thy hard and impenitent heart treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest up unto thy ſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath, Rom.</hi> 2. That's all a man gets by a hard heart. We reade of ſome, who when they ſhall come at the day of Judgment and knock ſaying, <hi>Lord, Lord, open to us;</hi> ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this anſwer, <hi>I know yee not, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part yee workers of iniquity; for when I was hungry yee fed me not,</hi> &amp;c. And doe you thinke that hard hearted ſinners ſhall receive any other anſwer then this, <hi>Depart</hi> &amp;c. For when I knocked at the doore of your hearts yee would not open to me, <hi>though my locks were wet with the dew of the night, therefore now will I not open to you.</hi> If you obſerve who they are whom Chriſt pronounceth bleſſed in his Sermon, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. You will finde that the moſt of thoſe which are there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153844:31"/>
are men of a temper as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to hardneſſe of heart, as white is to blacke. Our Saviour doth there pronounce them bleſſed who are poore in ſpirit, who mourne, who are meek, who do hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe; now theſe are the properties of broken hearted men, and there is nothing more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to them then a hard heart. Thus have we ſet before you the great evils attending upon a hard heart, namely, it hinders our accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God, ſuffers us not to reape benefit by what would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe do us good; and which is worſt of all, it ſhuts Heaven gate againſt it; which three things are moſt true concerning it, if by a hard heart you underſtand a heart not in the leaſt truly broken for ſinne &amp;c. Come we to the ſecond ſort of motives which we promiſed to ſpeake of, namely, ſuch as are taken from the benefit
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153844:32"/>
and uſefulneſſe of a broken heart. The benefits of a ſoft heart are as follow. 1. A ſoft heart is fit to receive any Grace, as ſoft wax is fit to receive any impreſſion. Metal being ſoftned by fire, is fit to be wrought in ſuch manner as the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer doth deſire to have it. When God is about to ſtampe his image upon the ſoule of a man, the worke of grace I meane) his manner is to prepare the heart thereunto by brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſoftning of it with the power of ſpirituall conviction. As thoſe we read of in the <hi>Acts</hi> who were pricked at heart, which is the firſt good we heare of them. It is ſaid of the ſpirit, that he ſhall convince firſt of ſinne, and then of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. As ground is prepared to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſeed by being firſt ploughed and broken up, ſo likewiſe is it with the hearts of men. It is ſaid That <hi>the humble God will teach,</hi> God makes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153844:32"/>
men teachable by humbling them, and then he teacheth them. <hi>Thou bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt man in cords of affliction, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt up inſtruction to him:</hi> why then? namely becauſe men are uſually moſt humble and broken in a time of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; and therefore moſt teacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at ſuch a time. Now it is a great matter to have our hearts fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive good, as Scripture counts fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, becauſe ſuch a heart is neare unto good; good doth as it were lye at the doore of ſuch a heart. Many mercies are long comming, becauſe the heart is long in fitting to receive them. And it is the manner of God in diſpenſing of mercies, firſt to look that the heart be made fit to receive them: as a wiſe Phyſitian will not give ſtrong phyſick till he have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the body of his patient for it; A ſmith will not ſtrike his iron till he have firſt made it hot, and ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of impreſſion from his blow.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153844:33"/>
Though God could perfect ſeverall kinds of worke in an inſtant, yet it is his manner to doe things gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, as firſt to fit men for mercies, and then to beſtow mercies upon them, <hi>humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God that he may lift you up in due time.</hi> If God give men good things before ſuch time as they are fit for them, he gives them uſually in wrath and not in mercy, for their hurt and not for their good. It is therefore a great benefit to have our hearts fit to receive good. So much of the firſt motive. 2. God will take up his abode in thy heart, if it be an humble heart; yea Chriſt will come, and the ſpirit will come and take up their abode in thy heart, if it be a ſoft heart. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>Thus ſaith the high and holy one, I dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of an humble and contrite heart, to revive the heart of the contrite ones.</hi> Now this
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153844:33"/>
is an expreſſion which ſpeakes much intimacy and nearneſſe for God to ſay that he dwells with them that are of an humble ſpirit. It is a ſteppe towards familiarity to dwell in the ſame towne, a further ſteppe to dwel the next doore to any neighbour; but beyond either of theſe, to dwell in the ſame houſe with any friend; how happy would a ſick man think himſelfe if he had an able Phyſitian dwelling conſtantly in the houſe with him, ſo as to be alwayes at hand when he hath any occaſion to make uſe of him. God dwels with broken hearted ſinners for that very end that he may revive them. If any friend in whoſe company you take great delight, ſo much indeed that you are not well without him, ſhould ſay, well, rather then you ſhall be melancholly for want of my company, I will even come dwell with you for altogether; would you
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153844:34"/>
not count it a great priviledge? how much greater priviledge is it to have God, and Chriſt, and the ſpirit dwel with us? Oh! who would loſe ſuch a priviledge rather then be at the paines to breake a hard heart? 3. An humble, a ſoft heart is in the beſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to be freed from ſinne. Looke how it is with the ground whileſt it is hard and faſt bound with froſt, there is no getting up the weedes if you would ever ſo faine; but when the raine deſcends upon it and ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens it, then you may pluck them up with eaſe. Sinne is bound up in the hearts of men whoſe hearts are hard, as weedes are bound in the ground in froſty weather, but when it wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſoft it may be plucked up by the rootes. God doth ſometimes ſuffer ſinne to continue in greater ſtrength and vigour in the hearts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then it otherwiſe ſhould, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to humble them, as knowing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153844:34"/>
that nothing can be matter of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter humiliation to a gracious heart then the power and ſtrength of ſin within it. Some thinke that by the meſſenger of Sathan which was ſent to buffet <hi>Paul,</hi> that he might not be puffed up with revelations, we are to underſtand ſome ſinne whereunto he was tempted, as a meanes to keep him humble; ſeeing then it is the manner of God ſometimes to break the hearts of good men by ſuffering their ſinnes to remaine in a great meaſure unſubdued (as ſome good men that are ſubject to violent paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, penſiveneſſe, and diſcontent of ſpirit) broken heartedneſſe muſt needes make way for the delivering men from the Tyranny of their ſins; for if you take away the cauſe of ſins continuance in good men which is oftimes the want of due humiliation and brokenneſſe of heart, the effect will follow. 4. A ſoft heart is fit to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153844:35"/>
receive all ſorts of good things. <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> is ſaid to have <hi>prepared the way of Chriſt,</hi> now you know the great Doctrine which <hi>John</hi> inſiſted upon was repentance or broken heartedneſſe; as being very prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the great worke of Chriſt, which was <hi>to binde up the broken hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and to proclaime liberty to the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, to bring the glad tidings of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the world.</hi> Tidings of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning grace is moſt acceptable and welcome to a broken heart. A bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart is fit for comfort, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, mercy, grace, and indeed what not that is truely good. If you would know in what reſpect a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart is moſt fit for any kinde of good, take this briefe account of it. 1. A broken heart ſtands in the moſt need of mercy, as comfort, &amp;c. A man is then moſt fit for meate and drinke when he is moſt hungry and thirſty; and ſo ſtands in the greateſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153844:35"/>
neede of it. He that hath not ſo good an appetite is not ſo fit to eate. 2. A ſoft heart is in the leaſt danger of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hurt by mercies, of being ſpoiled with kindneſſe; as we ſometimes ſay of children, they are ſpoyled with kindneſſe. It is not ſo apt to be puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up with mercies and to turne them into wantonneſſe as others are. 3. It receiveth mercy moſt thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and in that reſpect is moſt fit for mercy. Beggars by how much lower they are brought thorough want, by ſo much more thankefull will they be for any ſmall almes that is given them; whereas thoſe that are not ſenſible of much want begin to looke bigge if you offer them a ſmall matter. 4. Broken hearted Chriſtians make the beſt uſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements of their mercies, and therefore are moſt fit for mercy. They who thinke themſelves moſt unworthy to receive are alwayes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153844:36"/>
moſt carefull what and how to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp;c. 5. The fifth benefit of a ſoft heart is, a ſoft heart is moſt fit to doe any thing that is good, as to pray, heare, receive the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or performe any other duty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably. Indeed no heart but a ſoft heart is fit for duties, or can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them as they ought to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Prayer that proceedes not from a broken and contrite heart, though it be joyned with faſting, is as no prayer, no faſt in the ſight of God. If we be frequent in hearing the word; and have not our hearts broken and humbled thereby, we loſe the benefit of that duty. So likewiſe, if we come to the Lords Table, and then behold the body of Chriſt broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with unbroken hearts, we ſhall goe away as empty as we came, and do God as little ſervice in coming as if we had ſtaid away. And it muſt needs be ſo that a ſoft heart
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153844:36"/>
ſhould be moſt fit for duty, becauſe an humble ſelf abaſing temper is the beſt poſture for the ſoule to draw nigh to God; and not onely ſo, but this is further obſervable, namely, that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and brokenneſſe of ſoule fills men with zeal and activity for God; an humble heart thus thinkes with it ſelfe, I have hitherto beene very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, it is little ſervice, ſcarce worth ſpeaking of, that God hath had from me as yet; Oh how ſhall I redeeme time for God? how ſhall I make amends for my former baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and uſeleſneſſe? If God will but honour my utmoſt endeavour to be any wayes inſtrumentall for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, how happy ſhall I account my ſelfe, &amp;c. 6. The ſixth and laſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of a ſoft heart is, that it doth fit for a Kingdome, for Heaven and happineſſe. We read of being made meete to be partakers of the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in light; now
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153844:37"/>
brokenneſſe of a heart is a thing greatly conducing to the meetneſſe for an inheritance in light there ſpoken of. And that it is ſo, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, if we ſhall but conſider what is the worke and employment of Saints and Angels in Heaven. Is it not to admire and adore God, and to ſing everlaſting Hallelujahs? Now, who ſo fit to praiſe and to admire God, as broken hearted humble men. I can but thinke how poore humble hearted Chriſtians will ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and aſtoniſhed at the day of judgement, when God ſhall call them to his right hand, when Chriſt ſhall bid them ſit downe together with him, and judge the world. Do you thinke they will not be full of ſuch thoughts as theſe? Alas, what were we, or what are we, that God ſhould thus delight to honour us; that we ſhould be made Kings and Queenes unto God, when thouſands
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153844:37"/>
of the great ones of the world are caſt downe to hell. Surely they will cry out, <hi>Not unto us O Lord, not unto us, but to thy name be all the Praiſe and Glory.</hi> For by grace we are ſaved: by free grace alone are we ſaved; Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah. Thus have we ſet before you the ſeverall benefits of a ſoft heart, ſo much ſhall ſuffice by way of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, to put us upon endeavouring after the getting of ſoft hearts. <hi>Qu.</hi> But peradventure ſome will be ready to aske. How may we come by ſoft hearts, which we have heard to be ſacrifices ſo acceptable to God? By what meanes may we attaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto? <hi>Anſ.</hi> That it may be attained in the uſe of meanes, ſuch Scriptures ſeeme to ſignifie wherein God cals upon us, to rend our hearts, and to plow up the fallow ground of our hearts, &amp;c. Now the meanes to be uſed are as follow. 1. <hi>Meanes.</hi> We muſt attend upon the word of God.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153844:38"/>
For that is Gods hammer to breake the heart, and we muſt heare it with reverence, faith, and diligence, elſe it will harden our hearts and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our condemnation. It had wont to be no ſtrange thing to heare of hard hearts broken by the power of Gods word: ſometimes ſeverall in ſome one towne or village, and that within the ſpace of a few years. There is the ſame efficacy in the word now as was then, were it not that the prejudice which is in the minds of men againſt it, and great neglect and contempt of it did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the benefit which they might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe receive by it. That it is the proper worke of the word of God to ſoften mens hearts (I meane as an inſtrument in the hand of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) I may make appeare from this experiment: you ſee when the word of God doth not ſoften mens hearts, uſually nothing elſe doth, the worke
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153844:38"/>
remaines undone. Men ordinarily carry hard hearts with them to their graves, when they will not make uſe of the word of God wherewith to breake them. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 12. <hi>The word of God is quick and powerfull, and ſharper then any two edged ſword, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing even to the dividing of ſoul &amp; ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow, &amp;c. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> prayes that God would ſanctifie him by his truth, his word is truth. Now brokenneſſe of heart is a great part of ſanctification, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Meane,</hi> we muſt take away that or thoſe ſins which doe harden our hearts: Sin is the great cauſe of hardneſſe of heart. It is like ſome evill humour which is got to a head, and cauſeth a great ſwelling and hardneſſe. There is no mollifying the place until ſuch time as the evill humour which is in it be either diſſolved or diſſipated. There are ſome kinde of ſins which doe more eſpecially conduce to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153844:39"/>
hardning of mens hearts; as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſcandalous ſins, ſins againſt knowledge, ſins which have much of a mans underſtanding and will in them; deliberate ſins, ſins commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon very ſlender temptations; delightfull ſins, cuſtomary ſins, ſins which begin to juſtifie themſelves, and to put men upon pleading their cauſe, or at leaſtwiſe extenuating and making light of them. It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for a man to keepe a tender conſcience, if he will entertaine any one ſinne as his conſtant welcome gueſt. I might ſhew you ſeverall wayes whereby ſinne doth harden mens hearts. One is this: any ſinne that a man doth allow himſelf doth as it were ſhade his ſoule, that is, keepe off the warme beames of the light of Gods countenance which would otherwiſe ſhine upon it; you ſee how it is with the high wayes, ſuch as lye open to the ſun beames
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153844:39"/>
are ſoone melted, though there have beene ever ſo great a froſt; but thoſe places that are in the ſhade when the Sun is kept off by hedges or the like, continue to be hard when all the reſt are thawed. Sinne intercepts the light of Gods countenance, keepes back the warme rayes of the Sun from ſhining upon the ſouls of men, which is the moſt effectuall meanes to thaw and melt them of any other. Sinne breedes ſtrangeneſſe betwixt God and men, cauſeth fallings out between them; now as it is with friends, when there is any falling out or ſtrangeneſſe betweene them, they begin to be hardned againſt one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and they can ſpeake and doe that againſt each other without any trouble, which they could not do at another time, upon any termes, &amp;c. 3. <hi>Meane.</hi> It were good to call to minde every night what have beene our failings that day &amp; be humbled
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153844:40"/>
before God for that or thoſe ſins whatſoever they have been. We ſay, <hi>Gutta cavat lapidem,</hi> Continuall dropping upon makes the hardeſt ſtone become hollow, ſo the moſt ſtony heart would probably become ſoft by the continuall dropping of daily humiliation, and ſelfe exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. If the Sun begin to ſhine out by that time it hath frozen but a day or ſo, it will preſently thaw it. So it is good for us to thaw the ice of our hearts before it have beene ſo long frozen that it will beare; you know when ice is come to that paſſe, men doe walke or ride upon it without feare. He that ſhall but ſeldome call himſelfe to an account for his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, will goe nigh to grow ſo bold in the interim that he will be paſt feare of what conſcience can ſay to him: yea he will alſo goe nigh to have forgotten many ſins which might be matter of deepe humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153844:40"/>
to him, if they were freſh in his memory. Beſides, that ſinne doth oftimes looke moſt ghaſtly upon men, and moſt like it ſelfe ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the commiſſion of it, whileſt all circumſtances are yet before them: whereas the ſenſe and apprehenſion of it is apt to weare out by degrees, and like meat, that hath laine long in the ſtomack, it begins to be dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by little and little, till at length they complaine no more of it. If <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did every day call to minde a ſin committed long before, as that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſeemes to imply, <hi>my ſinne is ever before me, &amp;c.</hi> How much more ſhould we each day call to minde the ſins of the preſent day? 4. <hi>Meane.</hi> We muſt labour to ſee our miſery by reaſon of ſinne. There is a world of miſery which attends ſinne; the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof might ſerve greatly to humble us. For you know miſery is a very humbling conſideration, 'tis
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153844:41"/>
hardly poſſible for a man to thinke himſelfe very miſerable, and yet be very proud at the ſame time. I need not put you upon conſidering what miſchiefe ſinne doth expoſe you to: it may ſuffice unto the breaking of our hearts, to think what miſery ſin hath actually brought upon us. It made <hi>Paul</hi> cry out, <hi>O wretched man that he was; &amp;c.</hi> Gods people count themſelves more miſerable upon the account of that body of ſinne which they carry about with them, then upon account of all the calamities in the world beſides. Croſſes could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make them miſerable were it not for ſinne; I meane, nothing like ſo miſerable as now they doe. It is their frowardneſſe and impatience which doubles and trebles every affliction. 5. <hi>Meane.</hi> We muſt conſider of the great mercy of God towards us, in giving us hope that we ſhall be freed from hell, and received up into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153844:41"/>
Some may thinke it ſtrange that the mercies of God ſhould be reckoned amongſt the meanes of breaking mens hearts. And yet there is nothing more true, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his goodneſſe and forbearance, not knowing that the goodneſſe of God leadeth thee to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? Paul</hi> was able to ſay <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25. <hi>I thanke God thorough Jeſus Chriſt, namely, for delivering of him from the condemning power of his ſinne;</hi> and yet he cryeth out in the verſe immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foregoing, <hi>O wretched man that I am, &amp;c.</hi> ſee <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>The grace of God which bringeth ſalvation hath appeared to all men, teaching us, that denying ungodlineſs we ſhould live ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, righteouſly, and godly, &amp;c.</hi> Obſerve that he ſaith, the grace of God which brings ſalvation appearing to him did teach him to deny ungodlineſſe, and to live godly, &amp;c. If an ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirit would ſet it ſelf to mourne
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153844:42"/>
over any offence committed by it, it could uſe no more effectuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive then the conſideration of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall favours and kindneſſes recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from them againſt whom the offence was committed. Now what greater favour is poſſible for a man to call to minde then this, that by the free grace of God in Chriſt he hath beene delivered from the wrath to come, and brought into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberty of the ſonnes of God. 6. <hi>Meane.</hi> We muſt beg a ſoft heart at the hands of God, for if we aſke it ſincerely we ſhall have it, God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promiſed that whatſoever we ſhall aſke in the name of Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, he will heare us. Therefore let us preſſe him with his promiſe, as we have cauſe. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God better then by going to him for certaine mercies concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which he delighteth to be ſought unto by the ſons of men: you
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153844:42"/>
know how well God approved of it when <hi>Solomon</hi> did aſke for wiſdome inſtead of aſking gold and ſilver &amp;c. Surely a petition put up for a ſoft heart will be every whit as accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or rather more, &amp;c. There are certain requeſts which if men would be earneſt with God in, and lay the ſtreſſe of their deſires upon, would be greatly beneficiall and advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to them farre beyond thoſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions which the moſt of men are wont chiefely to inſiſt upon, and urge with the greateſt ſtrength and heate of affection. A ſoft heart is one of thoſe, of which may be truly ſaid what is ſpoken concerning Faith, namely that it is more precious and (let me adde more rare) then gold. Well might the Scripture ſay, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>We know not what to pray for as we ought, &amp;c.</hi> It being the manner of moſt men to pray moſt for what they have leaſt need of, or will doe them
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153844:43"/>
leaſt good: and leaſt for them of which they ſtand in the moſt need, and from whence they might reape the greateſt good. If men be ſick, how earneſtly doe they pray for health, but if troubled with hard hearts how coldly doe they pray to have them ſoftned? He that prayeth for a ſoft heart is under the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of an excellent promiſe, namely, that God will take away the heart of ſtone, &amp; give a heart of fleſh, which promiſe ſurely is as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to the people of God in all ages, as that which was made to <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> which the Apoſtle cals upon all believers to make uſe of, and depend upon, viz. <hi>I will never leave thee nor forſake thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are two conſiderations Which may put us upon praying for ſoft hearts, beſides the promiſe of God, whereof we have ſpoken already: as firſt, we cannot glorifie
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153844:43"/>
God with hard hearts. Men of hard hearts do ſinne the greateſt honour and ſervice that is poſſible for men to doe it, and God the greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour and disſervice. I ſhall make it out to you thus: He that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſin, and is never troubled for it, or layeth it to heart doth upon the matter juſtifie it; and ſay in effect, that he hath no cauſe to be aſhamed; that ſinne is no ſuch ugly abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing as the Scripture repreſents it, and hereby he doth ſin as much credit and ſervice as in him lieth: and on the other hand, he diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth God as much, in that he makes light of breaking his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous law, as if it were a ſmal thing ſo to doe. You cannot ſlight any man more, then in making nothing of offending him, as if it were not a pin matter whether he were pleaſed or diſpleaſed. Now this were a very good argument for a man to plead
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:153844:44"/>
with God, in relation to the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a ſoft heart; Lord, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt I cannot but diſhonour thee, and honour ſinne thy great enemy in a high degree, ſo long as my heart continueth thus hard; wherefore I beſeech thee to ſoften it. 2. Men of ſoft and tender hearts are moſt like to be continued in the enjoyment of thoſe good things which God hath beſtowed upon them. Mercies beſtowed upon hard hearted men doe many times prove like the ſeed ſown in the ſtony ground, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.5, 6. which had no deep rooting, ſo that it ſoon ſprung up &amp; withered. Such mens mercies doe ofttimes ſoon wither. When men doe turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe, and take occaſion from the light of Gods countenance to waxe more hard and proud (as the Clay that is hardned by the Sunbeams) uſually God doth quickly withdraw the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153844:44"/>
light of his countenance from them, and leave them in darkneſſe; but when thoſe beames doe melt the heart, and make it more and more ſoft, God is pleaſed ofttimes to let them abide longer with us, being improved for that end whereunto they were ſent, &amp;c. This may encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us to pray for ſoft hearts, &amp;c. 6. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This may ſerve for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all thoſe who have broken and contrite hearts. Though men deſpiſe them, God will accept of them and love them. St. <hi>Iames</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves thoſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.2. who were full of their reſpects towards ſuch as came into their Aſſemblies with Gold rings and goodly apparell, but deſpiſed the poor, ſaying, <hi>ſtand here, or ſit under my foot ſtoole:</hi> thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating, that in this carriage of theirs, they were altogether unlike to God, who is no reſpecter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon any of thoſe accounts,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153844:45"/>
and yet he hath more reſpect unto ſome then unto others, namely, unto thoſe who are of broken and contrite hearts. Great perſons look that it ſhould be accounted a high reſpect, if they vouchſafe now and then to beſtow a viſit upon them that are poore; How much greater is the reſpect and condeſcenſion of the great God towards broken hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſinners, in that he vouchſafeth not onely to viſit them now and then, but to take up his abode with them, to dwel with them. Though God doe ſometimes retire himſelfe, ſo that a broken hearted Chriſtian feares he is departed (as a man may think one that lodgeth in his houſe is not within, when he keepes cloſe, not willing to be ſpoken with) yet he alwaies dwels with the broken heart, to revive the ſpirit of the humble and contrite. Let broken hearted Chriſtians be of good cheer,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153844:45"/>
they may ſafely call God and Chriſt <hi>Emanuel,</hi> that is, God with them, &amp;c. <hi>Obj.</hi> But will God ſhew mercy to, and accept of me, who am a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſinner? I cannot believe it. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, God wil ſhew thee mercy, if thou beeſt an humble ſoule. <hi>Obj.</hi> But I have been a grievous ſinner, a notorious liver, and therefore I am juſtly humbled for my ſins. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thou muſt not look upon thy ſelfe, as thou haſt bin, but as thou now art; if thou be humbled, the blood of Chriſt waſheth thee from all thy ſinnes, how many and great ſoever they have been. I doe not ſay, that thou oughteſt not to reflect upon thy former converſation, upon any account whatſoever. For you know that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did call to mind what he had been, namely, a blaſphemer, a perſecutor, an inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perſon, &amp;c. This he did in reference to the magnifying of Gods
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153844:46"/>
grace, in making him ſuch as he was by grace; but I ſay, that in a time of trouble and perplexity of ſpirit we ought to look upon the preſent hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of our ſouls, and broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our hearts, as a ground of joy and comfort. <hi>Obj.</hi> But I am not worthy that God ſhould ſhew me ſo much mercy as to accept of me. <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, nor ever wilt be worthy in thy ſelfe of any mercy, but God looks upon thee in Chriſt, and in him doth account thee worthy. Therefore goe to God in the name of Chriſt, that is the way to finde acceptance: For God is very ready to heare his peoples prayers, &amp; to grant their requeſts; and he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to heare when they call, and he takes delight to heare his people pray. Therefore this may encourage us to pray, for God wil hear. <hi>Obj.</hi> But will God heare and grant the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of all? <hi>Anſ.</hi> No. They muſt be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153844:46"/>
godly which do prevaile with God. They muſt be ſuch as doe not allow themſelves in any ſin whatſoever. <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not heare my prayers, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 66.18. Again, They that would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with God muſt pray in faith, and with earneſtneſſe. Again, They muſt be conſtant in prayer, and not give over praying. Again, they muſt put up their requeſts in the name of Chriſt, with thankfulneſſe for ſuch mercies as they have already recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>Obj.</hi> I hope I am Gods child, and I have prayed, but God heares not me. <hi>Anſ.</hi> God may have heard thee, though not at the ſame time that thou deſireſt, not in the ſame thing. There may be good reaſon for that. Thou muſt not tie God to thy time, nor to thy means. For God is wiſe, he doth delay the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our requeſts for ſeverall holy ends and purpoſes; as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:153844:47"/>
To try our faith, to humble us, to make us ſee the want of a mercy, that we may the better prize it when it comes, be more thankfull for it, and uſe it more to his glory. &amp;c.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:47"/>
                  <p>A Short CONFESSION OF FAITH: BY Mr. SAMUEL ROWLES, Maſter of Arts: LATE Fellow of <hi>Trinity Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge:</hi> And now Miniſter of <hi>Thiſtleworth</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Rothwell.</hi> 1652.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:48"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:48"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He enſuing confeſſion of faith (which was delivered by me ſome years ſince at my Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Kent</hi>) was not then intended or calculated for publick view, but meerely for that ſeaſon, occaſion, and Auditory. If after peruſall thereof thou ſhalt thinke it worthy keeping by thee (which I dare not ſay thou haſt any cauſe to do) doe not thank me for it, but rather thoſe friends of mine, who importuning me for more written copies then the little time I could ſpare from miniſteriall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments would afford them, did upon the matter compell me to expoſe both it and my ſelfe to common cenſure, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of it to the preſſe; which I was the leſſe unwilling to doe, in regard I
<pb facs="tcp:153844:49"/>
had a more then ordinary opportunity for ſuch a purpoſe, in as much as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Tract touching brokenneſse of heart was to paſse thorough my hands: which I thought not ſo bigge, but that it might well admit of an Appendix, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch an one as this; which was too too little to came forth by it ſelfe. I have printed it with confidence onely touching the undoubted verity and truth of all that is contained in it (elſe I had beene much to blame to have made &amp; ſtyled it the confeſſion, or profeſſion of my Faith) and I hope I am ſo far confident of that, as that I ſhould not refuſe to ſeale much of it with my bloud (God aſſiſting me, without whom I am unable to doe any thing, much more unable to ſuffer for the truth) if ever I ſhould be called thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Touching the phraſe and method of it, judge as thou pleaſeſt: In caſe thou ſhalt approve one or both, I ſhall thinke it thy candor, more then its deſert: and if thou diſapprove either, or both, I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:153844:49"/>
not ſay thou doſt me any wrong, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they may thinke of it whoſe love and groundleſse reſpects to me may cauſe them to prize what is mine farre above the meaſure of its reall worth. I have gone the way of a generall dedication unto whomſoever pleaſeth to reade this little ſummary of divine truths; partly, becauſe I thought it too ſmall a worke wherewith particularly to preſent my beſt friends; and partly, becauſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and places whereto I am obliged are more then I could gratifie at once; and of three places whereto I am much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted, I knew not which to ſingle out to begin with: (namely, <hi>Trinity Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi>) where I had the greateſt part of my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity education, and encouragements, and was ſeverall yeares together happy under the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a moſt pious and prudent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and in the Society of as deſerving Fellowes, I ſpeake it without the leſt tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of flattery or partiality, as I believe
<pb facs="tcp:153844:50"/>
either <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity hath any, from whom I did all along receive more love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, then I ſhall be ever able to deſerve or requite. The next place, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a debtor to was <hi>Weſt Farleigh</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> where I was much ingaged to the worthy Knight of that ſhire, in whoſe family I there dwelt, and to his religious conſort, for the great affection they did beare to me, not to omit the reverend and godly miniſters of thoſe parts from whom I received my Ordination, together with many reſpects and encouragements from firſt to laſt in that place, where God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me to beſtow the firſt fruits of my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial labours. Nor am I leſſe engaged to the inhabitants of <hi>Thiſtleworth,</hi> for whoſe ſoules God hath ſet me to watch theſe two or three laſt yeares, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst whom I yet continue, I bleſs God, with leſs gaineſaying and more generall acceptation from them then many, not to ſay the moſt of my brethren, doe in their ſeverall places. It is the Lords doing
<pb facs="tcp:153844:50"/>
and marvellous in my eyes, knowing my ſelfe to be the unworthyeſt of all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervants of my Lord and maſter Chriſt, I ſay, not knowing which of theſe three places (for I have not time to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion perſons) I am moſt obliged to and conſequently ſhould begin with, I have made my dedication incluſive of all my friends (who are moſt like to be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hereof) but not excluſive to others, if they alſo pleaſe to reade it. Touching the worke it ſelfe, I have onely this to ſay, namely, that I call to minde very few, if any branches of truth growing upon the root of this confeſſion, which I ſhould not thinke it very dangerous for any man to turne his back upon, or looke towards with an eye of meere indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or ſcepticall neutrallity. The reaſon it, becauſe I take them to be fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, which whoſoever denies or derogates from, doth in my opinion runne a great hazzard, and <hi>Sampſon</hi>-like take hold upon the pillar of that houſe, in the fall
<pb facs="tcp:153844:51"/>
whereof himſelfe is like to periſh, and cauſe many more (as he did) to periſh with him. Errors riſing up againſt truths but preter fundamentals, doe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times prove of ſad conſequence to the Church and ſtate in which they are held; but fundamentalls alwayes much more hurtfull and prejudiciall to the ſoules of them that hold them. Wherefore, let thou and I receive each divine truth in the love thereof, leſt we be given up by God to ſtrong deluſions, to believe lies (a judgement ordinarily inflicted upon the wantons of this unſetled age) which that we may never be, is the hearty prayer of him who is,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine in the ſervice of the Goſpel, SAMUEL ROWLES.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Study in</hi> Thiſtleworth, <date>
                           <hi>March 26. 1651.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153844:51"/>
                  <head>A SHORT CONFESSION OF <hi>FAITH.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Believe there is a God,<note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God.</note> and but one, who is an infinite ſpirit, one in eſſence, three in perſons, truly though, not fully, made known to us by his glorious attributes of wiſdome, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Juſtice, mercy &amp;c. which are not ſo many qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in God, as in men they are) but his very eſſence thus repreſented to us, he being Holineſſe, Juſtice and Mercy it ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153844:52"/>
of perſons, or Subſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ariſeth from three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall incommunicable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, wherewith the divine eſſence is clothed, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable property of the father being to beget, of the ſon to have bin begotten, of the Holy Ghoſt to have proceeded from the Father and the Son. Yet are all theſe three perſons coequal, coeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential, coeternal, as the Sun and the light are contempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, though light do ſtreame from the Sun. I further doe believe, that the Heavens, the earth, and the great deepe, with all things contained in all, and every of them (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther living or without life, are the workemanſhip of his hands by the onely word of his power in time created
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153844:52"/>
out of nothing. As alſo that God did from all eternity foreknow and pre-ordaine all thoſe things which have or ſhall come to paſſe in time, and both hath and will by his executive power give be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto all ſuch things in his own fulneſſe of time, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he had decreed and reſolved upon in himſelfe from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity.<note place="margin">Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> Onely the decree of God concerning ſin, I ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly believe to be meerely a permiſſive decree, which he doth not proſecute and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue by the exerting of any ſuch poſitive power or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality as in other caſes,<note place="margin">Sin.</note> (for ſinne hath no efficient cauſe, but ſprings from meere defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency or defectiveneſſe, which were flat blaſphemy to aſcribe to God who is all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153844:53"/>
light, and in him no darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at all) but meerely ſuffereth to be and for holy ends and purpoſes (ſome of which we may partly gueſſe at) doth refuſe to let and hinder, though it be in the power of his hands to doe it. God is no wayes bound to ſtay the hands of men, when they ſtretch them forth to their own ruin, nor can he be ſaid to tempt any man, when he is tempted and drawne away of his owne hearts luſts, the Lord meane time refuſing to prevent or returne that his captivity. We deny not that God doth concurre to thoſe actions which are ſinfull, but not to the ſinfulneſſe of thoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As he that ſtriketh a lame horſe makes him goe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153844:53"/>
but doth not make him halt, for that proceeds meerely from his lameneſſe. He that playeth upon an untuned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument with a skilful hand is the cauſe of the ſound, but not of the jarring; for that it jarres, proceeds meerly from the untunedneſſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, and not from the unskilfulneſſe of ſuch a Muſician. There is ſomething in every evil action which is good, namely, its naturall being as it is a phyſicall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo farre forth it is from God, but the morall pravity and irregularity of it is from man alone. We alſo grant, that God doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lay ſtumbling blocks in the way of ſinners, as it is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.20. but yet he only ſuffereth, and no wayes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153844:54"/>
them to fall, or thruſts them downe. A man may walke if he be very carefull without falling, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtumbling blocks ſhould lye in his way. That God is onely the author of the oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſion, and hath no hand in the ſinne it ſelf, is intimated to us in that paſſage of the Lords prayer, in which we are taught thus to ſpeake, Leade us not into temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but deliver us from evil; &amp; not, lead us not into evil, but deliver us from tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; implying, that though we are lead into temptation by God, yet not into evil, not into ſinne, though he offer the temptation yet he onely ſuffereth the ſinne. I ſpeake nothing to the prejudice of Gods providence in diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153844:54"/>
of ſinne as well as other occurrences; for God may onely permit the commiſſion of ſinne, and yet diſpoſe of ſinne committed in ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viency to his own Glory. But to proceede from Gods permiſſive decree to his poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive providence. I believe it to have ſuch an univerſall influence upon all the affairs of the world, that the moſt inconſiderable paſſages and occurrences are ordered and diſpoſed thereby, inſomuch that not a haire can fall from our heads, or two ſparrows light upon the ground with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. Concerning the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God with Angels and men,<note place="margin">Angels.</note> which are of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt remarkable, I thus believe: Firſt, as touching Angels that they were all of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153844:55"/>
them created by God pure and ſpotleſſe ſpirits, an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of being above men, of a more Noble and active con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; in which eſtate many of them yet continue (and are probably confirmed by Chriſt therein) being pure flames, miniſtring to him that is the conſuming fire; as alſo pitching their Tents about the godly, and attending upon their good and ſafety) but others of them thorough affectation (as is conceived) to have been equall with God, fell downe from Heaven, like lightning: that is, were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced downe from thence, (as fire, which naturally tends upwards, is, when it light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, driven downwards by the violence of the breaking
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153844:55"/>
cloud, and that thoſe who kept not their ſtanding are reſerved in chaines of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the judgement of the great day, God having made no proviſion for their reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, as he did for raiſing up the tabernacle of <hi>Adam,</hi> which was fallen. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning man (the next creature to Angels in point of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and excellency) the ſpirit of God ſpeaking in the word hath thus perſwaded me,<note place="margin">Man.</note> (namely) that God at firſt did make him righteous, ſtamped his own image upon him, gave him freedome of will with an indifferency to good or evill, put him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a capacity of ſtanding (though not into an impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of falling) made a Covenant of workes with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153844:56"/>
him, that in doing he ſhould live; gave him a poſitive law (beſides that which was written in his heart) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to try his obedience; which law he wilfully tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and we in him; (that one <hi>Adam</hi> being all of us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatively, and after a ſort really, foraſmuch as we were all in his loines) and by that his tranſgreſſion brought a curſe upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his poſterity, yea his poſterity upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and all other creatures inferior to them, which are ſaid to be made ſubject to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity by reaſon of him who ſubjected them, that is man <hi>(viz.)</hi> obnoxiouſneſſe to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, the inflicting whereof upon thoſe for whom Chriſt interpoſeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153844:56"/>
not, is moſt juſt; and had beene ſo in reſpect of all, if Jeſus Chriſt had not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, as will appeare if we conſider the hainouſneſſe of the ſinne,<note place="margin">Mans fall.</note> which did contain in it a manifeſt breach of all the commandments (though it may ſeem at the firſt view to have been of no ſuch mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude and malignity) or the incapacity of one man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that great weight of wrath which was due for it; or the relation wherein we ſtood to <hi>Adam</hi> being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of himſelfe, in a ſenſe ſufficiently proper, being bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, that is ſeeminally and radically in him. I ſay, theſe things conſidered, we may ſalve the juſtice of God, without having recourſe to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153844:57"/>
his Soveraigne power. It is no part of Gods Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor yet conſiſtent with his juſtice, to charge guilt upon innocent creatures; neither would or could the righteous God, who can doe no unrighteous thing have laid <hi>Adams</hi> ſin at our doore, had it not been our ſin as well as his. The woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fruits of that accurſed fall we have daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of,<note place="margin">The ſad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it.</note> in the univerſall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation of our natures diſplaying it ſelfe, and being too too legible in the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable darkneſſe of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings (for how ſmall a portion is it that we know of God, our ſelves, or the nature of thoſe creatures which are round about us, in compariſon of what we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153844:57"/>
might have knowne) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſſe of our wils (which take occaſion by the Law of God, to ſin out of meaſure ſinfully) diſorder of our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (which are fixed moſt when they ſhould be leaſt, or not at all; and leaſt when they ſhould be moſt of all; which alſo change their due centres, our love moving towards thoſe things which ſhould be the center of our hatred) erroneouſneſſe, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity, ſearedneſſe, defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and intereſſedneſſe of our conſciences, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual proneneſſe of the whole man unto that which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; as it is written, the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations or figments of the minds of men are evil, and onely evill, and that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. But to proceed, I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153844:58"/>
further believe, that God ſoone after the fall of man (probably ſo ſoone as that the Sun did hardly go down upon his wrath) diſcloſed that gracious deſigne which he had reſolved upon from everlaſting, of recovering &amp; ſaving ſome of the ſons and daughters of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Recovery.</note> by Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> who was exhibited (though ſomewhat obſcurely) in that glorious promiſe, <hi>the ſeede of the woman ſhall breake the head of the ſerpent;</hi> which words containe the tenour of the Covenant of grace, or ſecond Covenant which God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into with man ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding life and ſalvation upon the condition of believing, of which I ſhall ſpeake more hereafter. This ſecond Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153844:58"/>
was at firſt called no other then the promiſe of the bleſſed ſeede,<note place="margin">Severall names of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, with the reaſon of them.</note> 
                     <hi>viz</hi> when made knowne unto <hi>Adam</hi> in the words forementioned, namely, that the ſeede of the woman ſhould &amp;c. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it was called a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, when revealed to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and ratified by many ſolemnities. Afterwards it was ſtyled a Teſtament or Legacy, where in <hi>Moſes</hi> his time, it was ſealed with the bloud of Chriſt, who was ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pically ſlaine in the ſeverall ſacrifices; and now the new Teſtament, becauſe ſealed with the bloud of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe; which is a new ſeale in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the bloud of Chriſt typically ſhed, which was long before it. Other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153844:59"/>
there are of its being called the new Teſtament, though it be for ſubſtance the ſame with the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is very Goſpell as well as the new (for the Covenant of workes was never called a Teſtament, nor could beare that name) which we ſhall hint hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Touching the Promiſe, Condition, Mediator, and Seales of the new Covenant or Teſtament, I believe as followeth. Firſt, that the things promiſed to thoſe which are concerned in it, are Chriſt with all his rich purchaſes,<note place="margin">Covenant of grace, its promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> ſuch as are the gift of the ſpirit, pardon of ſin, healing of our natures, peace of conſcience and eternall happineſſe. New teſtament-promiſes are moſtly ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153844:59"/>
but thoſe of the old teſtament were more carnal, that is, more relating unto temporall and outward things. Secondly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That the condition of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,<note place="margin">Its condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not aſſurance, but faith. Aſſurance proved not eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith.</note> on which the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned promiſes are ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is Faith, I do not ſay aſſurance, for that Faith may be where aſſurance is not, is cleer to me from 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Theſe things have I written to you that believe on the name of the ſonne of God, that you may know that you have eternall life;</hi> and had their Faith beene Aſſurance, they would have knowne that they had had eternall life, (<hi>i. e.</hi> were heires of it without his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to them) and <hi>that yee may believe on the name of the ſonne of God,</hi> (that is, that you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153844:60"/>
may increaſe in faith. Now aſſurance being the higheſt pitch of faith, a ſpeaking the abſence of all doubting, doth admit of no increaſe: (Indeed viſion is beyond Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, but there is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of faith higher and greater then aſſurance) if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleife may be mingled with true faith, as appeareth from this place it may, as alſo from <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.24. when the man cryes out, <hi>Lord I believe, help my unbeliefe,</hi> there Aſſurance is not of the eſſence of true faith, but a higher degree of it for Aſſurance excludes all unbeliefe. I might adde, that the fruits of ſaving faith,<note place="margin">Faith.</note> as purifying of the heart, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Chriſt, &amp;c doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally appear to be in the hearts of many who are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153844:60"/>
farre ſhort of Aſſurance. But ſuch a Faith is required to bring us within the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as is an Affiance or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting innitency, or reſting of the ſoul upon Jeſus Chriſt exhibited in the promiſe for life and ſalvation, expreſſed in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> by truſting in the Lord, and ſtaying upon the name of God, when we ſit in darkeneſſe and ſee no light.</p>
                  <p>As for the effects of true faith, they are theſe: 1. It workes by love, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently puts men upon obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the commands; For thoſe that love God, wil keep his commandments, &amp; are indeed conſtrained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by the love of God ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in their hearts. So you ſee, that faith doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude but include obedience
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153844:61"/>
to the commands of God, wherein holineſſe conſiſts. Though we are juſtified by faith without workes, yet not by a faith which hath no works. Saving faith recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth Chriſt according to all his offices, as well as he is a King and Lord, as Prieſt and Saviour. Touching the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which is Chriſt, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve concerning him, as ſuch:<note place="margin">Mediator and his Offices.</note> 1. The duplicity of his nature, that he is God as wel as man, man as well as God. 2. The triplicity of his offices, namely, that he is 1. a King, having a Mediatorious Kingdom committed to him by God the Father, by vertue whereof he doth chiefly act and appeare in the Kingdom of grace, and ought princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153844:61"/>
and immediately to be addreſſed to, which King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom it is ſaid he ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after deliver up to God the Father, and then ſhall God be all in all. This Kingdom of his he doth adminiſter by certain outward means, and viſible diſpenſations, as the Word and Sacraments (as wel as by the inward opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Spirit) which whoſoever caſt off, in ſo doing doe in effect ſay, that they will not be ſubjects of Chriſt his Kingdom. 2. That he is a Prophet for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning and inſtructing of his Church, which yet he doth not ordinarily, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, but mediately, by thoſe Ordinances which he hath appointed in his Church, having given va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153844:62"/>
of gifts for the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. 3. That he is a Prieſt who hath offered up himſlfe a ſacrifice for us, did raiſe himſelfe from the grave within three daies by the power of his Godhead; ſhortly after aſcended up to Heaven, where he now ſets at the right hand of God the Father, alwaies making interceſſion for us. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſeales of the new Covenant (having ſpoken of the promiſe, condition, and mediator thereof.) I do this further believe, namely, that they were and are but two,<note place="margin">Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> properly called Seales or Sacraments, <hi>viz</hi> The Paſſeover and Circumciſion under the Old Teſtaments adminiſtration, Baptiſm and the Lords Supper under the
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:153844:62"/>
                     <hi>of God, &amp;c.</hi> He had ſaid verſ. 13. that <hi>Moſes</hi> did put a vaile upon his face, that the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not ſee to the end of thoſe things which are aboliſhed; that is, they could not ſee Chriſt who was the end of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall law, which is now aboliſhed by reaſon of that vaile which is not onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hearts of the Jewes at this day, but was then upon the face of <hi>Moſes;</hi> that is of <hi>Moſes</hi> his writings: which vaile was no other then the darkeneſſe and obſcurity of the manner in which the myſteries of the Goſpell were then delivered. They are ſaid to have had but the ſhadow of good things to come (the ſhadow of a man is ſo darke a repreſentation
<pb facs="tcp:153844:63"/>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153844:64"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:153844:64"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153844:65"/>
of him that he can never or very hardly be known by it) but we to ſee thoſe ſame things as in a glaſſe (we may as well know a man by the repreſentation of him in a glaſſe as if we ſhould ſee him face to face) and with open face too (which may ſignifie more light ſhining into the underſtandings of men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell then did in the time of the law) and to behold the glory of God, whereas they ſaw little of it in compariſon.<note place="margin">3. Efficacy</note> 3. In point of efficacy, the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment adminiſtration of the Goſpell doth excell. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in the old Teſtament were generally as trees growing in the ſhade except ſome few worthyes, ſuch as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153844:65"/>
believers under the new Teſtament diſpenſation are as trees growing in ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where the influence of the warm beames of the Sun may come at them without hinderance or interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Hence the time of the old Teſtament is called the time before the comming of Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Before Faith came (i. e.</hi> in that plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that it comes in the time of the new Teſtament) <hi>we were ſhut up unto the Faith which ſhould afterwards be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</hi> All which expreſſions doe ſpeake the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment adminiſtration of the Covenant of grace to have beene leſſe effectuall then is the new; ſome thinke that place <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.8. <hi>He that is feeble ſhall be as David, and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153844:66"/>
houſe of David ſhall be as God, as the Angell of God before them.</hi> I ſay ſome thinke that it is a promiſe of that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of grace which ſhall be in believers in the time of the new Teſtament above what was in the generallity of old Teſtament believers. 4.<note place="margin">4. Change of Seales a a fourth difference.</note> The adminiſtration of the Covenant of grace under the new Teſtament differeth from that of the old in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the alteration of ſeales, of which we have ſpoken already. Thus have I declared my perſwaſions touching the Covenant of grace, and the ſeverall things belonging thereunto. After the publication of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Covenant in that firſt promiſe, the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall breake the head of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153844:66"/>
the Serp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt, God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſeverall piece-meales, and in ſeverall manners, to make knowne himſelfe to thoſe who lived in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of the world, declaring himſelfe to them ſometimes by a voyce from Heaven, as the law was given from <hi>Mount Sinai;</hi> ſometimes by viſions, other times by dreames, other times by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies; ſometimes by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of things not prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall; which things were afterwards written for our inſtruction, upon whom the ends of the world are come, that we thorough Faith and patience might inherit the promiſes;<note place="margin">Scriptures.</note> which writings are commonly knowne by the name of the <hi>Bible</hi> or holy ſcriptures, concerning which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153844:67"/>
I thus believe (namely) that they were inſpired by God, and left as a rule of faith and manners ſo to continue to the worlds end, and are able to make the man of God, perfect to every good word and worke. As alſo, that we who live under the Goſpel, ought ſtill to have reſpect unto that part of Scripture which is called the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. My reaſons for it are theſe: 1. That exhortation of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reaſons why the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be ſtill reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</note> (which is meant of the old Teſtament, for then they had no other) <hi>for in them yee thinke</hi> (that is you your ſelves are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as well as the truth is) <hi>that yee have eternall life,</hi> that is, the way to eternall life, which is Chriſt himſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153844:67"/>
to you, as appeareth to be the meaning by the following words; and they are they which teſtifie of me. Who dare reject that word which gives teſtimony to Chriſt? if you ſay that the ceremoniall law did ſo, I anſwer, that the obſervation of it now, would be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing againſt Chriſt, as if he were not already come in the fleſh but expected hereafter, and therefore it is aboliſhed. 2. The identity or ſameneſſe of the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is another reaſon why I contend for having reſpect to it. The old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe both treate of the ſame ſubject, namely Chriſt, and the way of ſalvation by Faith in him, though with ſome difference of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153844:68"/>
&amp;c. It is ſaid that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt did all the prophets beare witneſſe. 3. The fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent quotations which are in the new Teſtament out ot the old, as if Chriſt himſelfe and his Apoſtles had but commented upon the old Teſtament, and would not urge things upon the beliefe of thoſe to whom they Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched without good warrant and teſtimony from <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets. 4. I am induced to have reſpect to the old Teſtament from this undeniable principle, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that as it is dangerous to plant what God hath not planted, ſo much more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to plucke up what God hath planted, till he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to doe it with his own right hand. Now we doe
<gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                        <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153844:68"/>
eſtranging them to the world, affecting them to, and enflaming them for God. 2. Touching the duties of men towards God,<note place="margin">The du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of men towards God.</note> I thus believe, <hi>viz.</hi> That all ſorts of men are bound to love, feare, ſerve, and truſt in him with all their hearts and ſoules, by vertue of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received from him, in conjunction with all other mercyes, as alſo for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued preſervation (which is equivalent to a continuall creation) of their beings and wel-beings. But that there is a double tye upon belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to give up their whole ſelves, ſouls and bodies unto God. For they are leaſt of all their own, being Gods, not onely by creation and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture (as all wicked men
<pb facs="tcp:153844:69"/>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:153844:70"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153844:70"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:153844:71"/>
are) but by redemption alſo, he having bought them with a price. The manner in which they are to ſerve God for the externall part of it, I conceive to be in the way of his ordinances, <hi>viz</hi> by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reading,<note place="margin">Singing of Pſalms, what it is.</note> hearing, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating, ſinging of Pſalmes (which is meditating and praiſing of God with the voyce lifted up for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and provoking of greater cheerefulneſſe, and affording further leiſure by due pauſing and treatable delivery for divine conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) not to omit atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon God in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of baptiſme and the Lords ſupper.<note place="margin">Right manner of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, what it is.</note> As for the manner of performing theſe duties (in which the life and ſpirit of religion doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153844:71"/>
they are to be done in Faith from Goſpell motives, to ſpirituall ends, by way of teſtifying our thankefulneſſe and the rule of them is to be the word of God. I might adde that God is to be ſerved in the exerciſe of all graces, as Faith, humility, patience, ſelf-denyall, zeale,<note place="margin">Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men from God. Of all men.</note> &amp;c. which are the fruits of the ſpirit of God within us. Laſtly, I ſhall conclude with my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions touching what men are to expect from God: 1. In generall, 2. In ſpeciall. In the generall, all men are to looke for a ſummons by death to a particular appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and accompt, for the reſurrection of their bodies after they have laine awhile in the grave, for a citall of ſoule and body to appeare
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153844:72"/>
before God at the day of the great Aſſize to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the deedes done in their bodies. Theſe things are to be expected in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon both of good and bad.<note place="margin">Of wicked men.</note> But to deſcend to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: As for men continuing in unbeliefe and impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I know nothing belongs to them but a certaine dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expectation of fury and vengeance, to be poured out upon all the adverſaries, and that having compaſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſparkes they ſhould have this at length at Gods hand, namely, to lye downe in ſorrow, and that their ſoules, being at the great day reunited to their bodies, ſhould return to hell, whence they came, the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of eternall condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153844:72"/>
being irrecoverably paſt upon them. <hi>Depart yee curſed, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Of good men in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the preſent life, and of that which is to come.</note> But as for Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, they have ſomething to expect from God here, and ſomething hereafter. Here they expect ſome things for themſelves and other things for the Church; for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the keeping of them by the power of God to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, the peace of God to guard their hearts. For the Church, The preſence of Chriſt with it by his ſpirit to the worlds end, the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Serpents head, and putting downe of the man of ſinne, and all other enemies of Chriſt which ſhall be made his footſtoole. For hereafter, they expect that their ſoules being joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their bodies which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153844:73"/>
ſhall be made conformable to the glorious body of Chriſt, ſhall re-enter into their manſions of glory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an intire glorified eſſence (whereas but a part of them was before in glory) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard their judge, who is alſo their redeemer and ſurety, thus pronounce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, Well done good and faithfull ſervants, enter into your Maſters Joy.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153844:73"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
